<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://eminichiello67.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://eminichiello67.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-04-21T14:22:07+00:00</updated><id>https://eminichiello67.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Emilio Minichiello</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Diffeological Spaces, Part 3</title><link href="https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diffeological Spaces, Part 3" /><published>2023-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_3/"><![CDATA[<p>Let us now finally delve into the definition of a diffeological space. Before we do that, we need some preliminary notions.</p>

<p><strong>Definition</strong>: A <strong>cartesian space</strong> is a finite dimensional smooth manifold diffeomorphic to \(\mathbb{R}^n\) for some \(n \geq 0\). Given a set \(X\), a <strong>parametrization</strong> is a set function \(p : U \to X\) where \(U\) is a cartesian space. If \(M\) is a finite dimensional smooth manifold, and \(\mathcal{U} = \{ U_i \subseteq M \}\) is a collection of subsets of \(M\), we say that \(\mathcal{U}\) is a <strong>good open cover</strong> if each \(U_i\) is a cartesian space, every finite intersection \(U_{i_0} \cap \dots \cap U_{i_n}\) is either empty or a cartesian space, and \(\bigcup_i U_i = M\).</p>

<p><strong>Definition</strong><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>: Given a set \(X\), a <strong>diffeology</strong> \(\mathcal{D}_X\) on \(X\) consists of a set of parametrizations \(p: U \to X\) satisfying the following three conditions:</p>
<ol>
  <li>All parametrizations with domain \(\mathbb{R}^0\) belong to \(\mathcal{D}_X\), namely all the points of \(X\),</li>
  <li>If \(p : V \to X\) is a parametrization, and \(f: U \to V\) is a smooth map between cartesian spaces, then the composition \(p \circ f\) belongs to \(\mathcal{D}_X\),</li>
  <li>If \(p: U \to X\) is a parametrization, \(\mathcal{U} = \{ U_i \subseteq U \}\) is a good open cover of \(U\) and \(p \vert_{U_i} \in \mathcal{D}_X\) for every \(U_i \in \mathcal{U}\), then \(p \in \mathcal{D}_X\).
If \(\mathcal{D}_X\) is a diffeology, then we call a parametrization \(p : U \to X\) that belongs to \(\mathcal{D}_X\) a <strong>plot</strong>. A <strong>diffeological space</strong> consists of a pair \((X, \mathcal{D}_X)\) of a set equipped with a diffeology.</li>
</ol>

<p>Given two diffeological spaces \((X, \mathcal{D}_X)\) and \((Y, \mathcal{D}_Y)\), a <strong>smooth map</strong> between them consists of a set function \(f : X \to Y\) such that if \(p : U \to X\) is a plot of \(X\), namely \(p \in \mathcal{D}_X\), then the composite map \(U \xrightarrow{p} X \xrightarrow{f} Y\) is a plot of \(Y\). Let \(\mathsf{Diff}\) denote the category of diffeological spaces with smooth maps.</p>

<p>Notice how simple these definitions are compared to the corresponding definitions of a smooth manifold! Really think about it, the definition of a manifold is really complicated. Its a kind of topological space (Hausdorff, second-countable), and it has all of these charts, which are homeomorphisms from cartesian spaces, and those charts have to be compatible in some way that’s really annoying to write symbolically, and then we consider the biggest collection (maximal atlas) of such charts compatible with the ones you’ve got, and then you call that a smooth structure. Okay, maybe if you are a seasoned differential geometer it isn’t so bad, but I remember spending <em>months</em> understanding the definition of a smooth manifold the first time I learned about it. There are so many nooks and crannies to get stuck on it. The definition of a diffeological space however, by comparison is clean and tidy. Same for the definition of smooth map.</p>

<p>Okay, that’s nice and all, but its just a definition. I can define whatever the hell I want, but its only interesting if it connects with things I care about. Well, suppose that \(M\) is a finite dimensional smooth manifold in classical differential geometry. Then we can consider the set \(\mathcal{D}_M\) of those parametrizations \(p : U \to M\) that are smooth as maps of smooth manifolds, in the sense of classical differential geometry. It turns out that \(\mathcal{D}_M\) satisfies the axioms of a diffeology. In other words, every finite dimensional smooth manifold is canonically a diffeological space. We call this the <strong>manifold diffeology</strong> on \(M\).</p>

<p>Even more powerfully, a function \(f: M \to N\) between finite dimensional smooth manifolds is smooth in the classical sense if and only if it is a smooth map in the sense of diffeological spaces between \(M\) and \(N\) equipped with their manifold diffeologies! This is proven in the <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Diffeology/Nb0xAAAAQBAJ?hl=en">diffeology textbook</a> in Article 4.3, and it implies that assigning the manifold diffeology to a manifold defines a fully faithful functor from the category of finite dimensional smooth manifolds to the category of diffeological spaces.</p>

\[\mathcal{D}_{(-)} : \mathsf{Man} \hookrightarrow \mathsf{Diff}.\]

<p>Intuitively, this means that we lose nothing by considering manifolds as diffeological spaces via their manifold diffeology. We could also characterize finite dimensional smooth manifolds as those diffeological spaces which have local diffeomorphisms to a fixed \(\mathbb{R}^n\) and satisfy some additional conditions.</p>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The astute reader will note that this is not the definition of a diffeogical space as given in the <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Diffeology/Nb0xAAAAQBAJ?hl=en">“Diffeology textbook”</a>. However, in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.11023">my paper</a>, I prove that the category of diffeological spaces as given in the Diffeology textbook and the category of diffeological spaces as given in the definition above are equivalent. The above definition is far more convenient to work with for my purposes. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math" /><category term="diffeological_spaces" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The definition of diffeological spaces]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diffeological Spaces, Part 2</title><link href="https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diffeological Spaces, Part 2" /><published>2023-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_2/"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s dive into the history of diffeological spaces. Note that this is a history very biased towards my interests in diffeology and leaves out many important developments in the theory.</p>

<ul>
  <li>(1973): Kuo-Tsai Chen wrote a <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1970846?origin=crossref">paper</a> where he introduced Chen spaces, a class of smooth spaces very similar to diffeological spaces, for the purpose of proving a “loop space deRham Theorem” (his words). This Theorem states that one can calculate the cohomology of the loop space of a manifold using a technique called “iterated integrals.” The important point here is being able to define differential forms on the loop space of a manifold, which is almost never a finite dimensional smooth manifold. While this is not directly relevant<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> to diffeological spaces, it shows that such ideas about generalized smooth spaces were “in the air.”</li>
</ul>

<ul>
  <li>(1980): Jean-Marie Souriau wrote a <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/bfb0089728">paper</a> where he introduced diffeological groups. His motivation was based in defining certain infinite dimensional smooth groups (such as groups of diffeomorphisms or symplectomorphisms) appearing in symplectic geometry.</li>
</ul>

<div align="center">
<figure>
<p><img src="../../../assets/img/souriau.jpeg" alt="axes" width="250" /></p>
  <figcaption>Figure 1: Jean-Marie Souriau.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>(1983): Souriau’s students Patrick Iglesias-Zemmour (PIZ) and Paul Donato write <a href="http://math.huji.ac.il/~piz/documents/EDGDFISLT.pdf">“Exemple de groupes différentiels : flots irrationnels sur le
tore”</a>, which studies what will become the most famous example of a diffeological space, the Irrational Torus. Later that year, Souriau gives the first general definition of a diffeological space in his paper <a href="http://math.huji.ac.il/~piz/documents-others/JMS-GDEPM-1983.pdf">“Groupes Differentiels Et Physique Mathematique”</a>.</li>
</ul>

<div align="center">
<figure>
<p><img src="../../../assets/img/iglesias-zemmour.jpeg" alt="axes" width="250" /></p>
  <figcaption>Figure 2: Patrick Iglesias-Zemmour.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>(1988): PIZ writes a <a href="http://math.huji.ac.il/~piz/documents/BCCED.pdf">preprint</a> showing that there is an obstruction between Cech cohomology and deRham cohomology for diffeological spaces given by the diffeological principal \(\mathbb{R}\)-bundles with connection. It is never published.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>(Late 1980s-2000s): PIZ develops a large amount of the theory of diffeological spaces in his thesis and several papers throughout this period. There are a couple of papers from other people, but overall not a large amount of activity.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>(2009): Baez and Hoffnung prove that diffeological spaces are precisely concrete sheaves on the site of open subsets of euclidean spaces in their paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0807.1704">“Convenient Categories of Smooth Spaces.”</a> This provides an important bridge connecting diffeology to sheaf theory.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>(2013): PIZ publishes the first (and currently only) textbook on diffeology, appropriately named <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Diffeology/Nb0xAAAAQBAJ?hl=en">“Diffeology.”</a> This helps attract a new generation of mathematicians to the subject.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>(2010s): There is a huge influx of interest in diffeology. Papers are written about diffeology with connections to <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0911.3212">mathematical physics</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1309.3001">Lie groupoid theory</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0903.2871">foliations</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1311.6394">homotopy theory</a>, and more. Some particularly important papers are written in this period.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Two definitions of tangent spaces, the internal and external, are given for diffeological spaces in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1411.5425">“Tangent Spaces and Tangent Bundles for Diffeological Spaces.”</a> by Christensen and Wu. They are shown to be isomorphic for manifolds, and agree with the usual definition of tangent space. They are shown not to agree in general, and many fascinating examples are given.</li>
      <li>A compactly generated model structure<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> is proven to exist for diffeological spaces by Kihara in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.06794">“Model category for Diffeological Spaces.”</a> In order to make this model structure work, Kihara alters the diffeology on simplices.</li>
      <li>A deep study of diffeological vector spaces is made in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.07564">“Diffeological Vector Spaces”</a> by Christensen and Wu. Many new fascinating examples of misbehaving diffeological spaces are given.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>(2021): Out of the pandemic sprouts the Monthly Global Diffeology Seminar and a website hub <a href="https://diffeology.net/">diffeology.net</a> for everything diffeology.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>(2020s): With the start of the new decade comes a newly energized and diverse community of diffeologists. Some notable papers are:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>In <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.12845">“Projective model structures on diffeological spaces and smooth sets and the smooth Oka principle”</a>, Pavlov settles in the negative a long-standing conjecture, he proves that there does not exist a model structure on diffeological spaces that is right transferred from the Kan-Quillen model structure on simplicial sets. Instead, he proves the existence of a right transferred model structure on all sheaves on \(\mathsf{Cart}\), which the category of diffeological spaces is a full subcategory of.</li>
      <li>Two important papers on diffeological groupoids are written, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09901">“Diffeological Morita Equivalence”</a> by van der Schaaf and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.12730">“Bicategories of Diffeological Groupoids”</a> by Watts, providing a solid framework for future work generalizing Lie groupoid theory.</li>
      <li>In <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02583">“Elastic Diffeological Spaces”</a> by Blohmann, a subclass of diffeological spaces, known as elastic diffeological spaces, is shown to admit a tangent category structure. This implies that elastic diffeological spaces have a Lie algebra structure on their set of vector fields, providing a “Cartan Calculus” for elastic diffeological spaces. This sets up a powerful framework for future work in symplectic geometry.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><br /></p>
<ul>
  <li>(2023): PIZ finally publishes his paper <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11856-023-2486-8">“Cech-deRham bicomplex in diffeology”</a> on the Cech-deRham obstruction for diffeological spaces that was originally written in 1988.<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>However, Iglesias-Zemmour writes in his <a href="http://math.huji.ac.il/~piz/documents/AITD.pdf">Introduction to Diffeology</a> (where I obtained much of this history) that diffeological spaces were “built on the model” of Chen spaces. Later work by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0802.2225">Stacey</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0807.1704">Baez-Hoffnung</a> showed how Chen spaces are directly comparable to diffeological spaces. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Another model structure was proven to exist on diffeological spaces in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.12842">“A model structure on diffeological spaces, I”</a>, though it took many years to develop and Kihara’s help in amending previous proofs. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I can’t help but mention that at the time of writing, there are four different versions of Cech cohomology for diffeological spaces in the literature. Indeed, there is PIZ’s, defined in his paper above. There is Krepski, Watts and Wolbert’s diffeological Cech cohomology given in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.01032">“Sheaves, principal bundles, and Čech cohomology for diffeological spaces”</a>. There is my version of Cech cohomology for diffeological spaces defined in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.11023">“Diffeological Principal Bundles and Principal Infinity Bundles”</a> which is called \(\infty\)-stack cohomology. Finally there is Ahmadi’s version of diffeological Cech cohomology given in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03251">“Diffeological Cech Cohomology.”</a> It is currently an open question as to whether any of these cohomologies agree for all diffeological spaces. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math" /><category term="diffeological_spaces" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some history of diffeological spaces.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diffeological Spaces, Part 1</title><link href="https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_1-copy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diffeological Spaces, Part 1" /><published>2023-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_1%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://eminichiello67.github.io/blog/2023/diffeological_spaces_1-copy/"><![CDATA[<p>For the first post on my blog, I thought it only appropriate to get started on some posts about diffeological spaces. This is the main subject of study in my PhD research, and will be the topic of my thesis. So in this post, I want to answer the question “What the hell is a diffeological space, and why should I care?”</p>

<p>Okay, so that’s actually two questions, and I will handle the second one (“why should I care?”) first. There are actually many different ways to approach this question, and rather than list a bunch of them, I’ll pick one for this post.</p>

<p>So imagine you are a differential geometer. Your research revolves around finite dimensional smooth manifolds, well behaved mathematical objects with a long history (something like 200 years) of study. You know that whatever tools you need, there will be something in the enormous toolbox of classical differential geometry to suit your needs. Hell, partitions of unity probably get you most of the way.</p>

<p>One day you come across some kind of smooth space, maybe a group of diffeomorphisms, or possibly an orbifold of some kind, which is not a finite dimensional smooth manifold! You want to prove some theorems about this misbehaving space, but when you flip through your textbooks on classical differential geometry, there’s nothing! All of its theorems are about finite dimensional smooth manifolds. You glance over at the dusty tome on your shelf about Banach manifolds, with its hundreds of pages of hardcore functional analysis, and cower in fear.</p>

<p>Okay, maybe that’s a little dramatic. But its something that happens all the time in differential geometry. The truth is, modern differential geometry wishes to study all kinds of crazy spaces that are not finite dimensional smooth manifolds. Yet, the way these crazy spaces are usually dealt with is in an ad hoc manner, and sometimes require lots of functional analysis. When a new kind of crazy space comes along, and we wish to study it, none of the tools we’ve developed thus far will help us. We need to redefine all the concepts of differential geometry we’d like to use on this new kind of crazy space.</p>

<div align="center">
<figure>
<p><img src="../../../assets/img/domain_of_diffeology.png" alt="domain of diffeology" width="500" /></p>
  <figcaption>Figure 1: from <a href="http://math.huji.ac.il/~piz/documents/AITD.pdf">Introduction to Diffeology</a>, by Patrick Iglesias-Zemmour</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>

<p>Diffeology is a new, modern framework for differential geometry that says “enough is enough, we need a big box of smooth spaces that includes manifolds and all kinds of crazy spaces us modern differential geometers care about, and we need a uniform way of reasoning about these spaces, and extending our old theorems to them.” This might sound like wishful thinking. What mathematics will guide us in this new world, far out from our cozy land of Euclidean spaces and tori? That tool is <strong>Category Theory</strong>.</p>

<p>You’ve probably heard about category theory already if you are looking at this blog, so I won’t bother trying to explain what it is, as any attempts by myself to do so would probably be embarassing anyway. Why category theory matters here is because there is a category staring us in the face. That category is \(\mathsf{Man}\), the category whose objects are finite dimensional smooth manifolds and whose morphisms are smooth functions between them.</p>

<p>This category <strong>sucks</strong>!</p>

<p>Indeed, the category \(\mathsf{Man}\) has finite products, transverse pullbacks and a few colimits (but noticeably not any coproducts between manifolds of different dimension!). This is not enough for the working category theorist or really for the working geometer. We want to glue things together willy-nilly, like for instance, this is my favorite example, take two copies of the real line, and glue them together at the origin. We’ll call this space the Axes.</p>

<div align="center">
<figure>
<p><img src="../../../assets/img/axes.png" alt="axes" width="300" /></p>
  <figcaption>Figure 2: Axes, the result of gluing two copies of \(\mathbb{R}\) at the origin.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>

<p>This is not a manifold! If it were, then it would be the colimit of the following diagram in \(\mathsf{Man}\).</p>

\[0 \rightrightarrows \mathbb{R} \sqcup \mathbb{R},\]

<p>where each map is the inclusion of the origin into either the left or right copy of \(\mathbb{R}\). But c’mon now, this is a simple space! We should be able to have the usual concepts of differential geometry (tangent spaces, bundles, deRham cohomology, etc.) apply to this thing!</p>

<p>Diffeology is an attempt to do just this. It provides us with a category, \(\mathsf{Diff}\), whose objects are diffeological spaces, which is complete, cocomplete, and locally presentable. If you don’t know what that means exactly, don’t worry about it. The point is that it is a wayyy better category than \(\mathsf{Man}\), it lets us glue stuff together however we like. Our friend the Axes is an object in this category, as are all finite dimensional smooth manifolds, and thus the diagram above can be considered in \(\mathsf{Diff}\), and its colimit is precisely Axes!</p>

<p>This was a super rough, motivational post. I’ll be back next time to delve into some more motivation and some of the history of diffeological spaces.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math" /><category term="diffeological_spaces" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The inaugural post! What is a diffeological space?]]></summary></entry></feed>